<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of dangerous consequence, from Sergeant Major Ogle, to Sir Nicholas Crisp at Oxford. As it was intercepted by Colonell Goodwin of the Parliaments forces. Together with the examination of the messenger, in the coller of whose doublet the said letter was found. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that this letter and examination be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>Ogle, Thomas, Sir, d. 1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E91_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869129</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90124)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E91[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of dangerous consequence, from Sergeant Major Ogle, to Sir Nicholas Crisp at Oxford. As it was intercepted by Colonell Goodwin of the Parliaments forces. Together with the examination of the messenger, in the coller of whose doublet the said letter was found. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that this letter and examination be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>Ogle, Thomas, Sir, d. 1671.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw: Husbands,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>February 27. 1642 [i.e. 1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter is signed: Theophilus Philobritanis [pseud.].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ogle, Thomas, --  Sir, d. 1671 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Crisp, Nicholas, --  Sir, 1599?-1666 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Goodwin, Arthur, 1593 or 4-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER OF Dangerous Conſequence, <hi>From Sergeant Major</hi> Ogle, <hi>to Sir</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Criſp <hi>at Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was Intercepted by Colonell <hi>Goodwin</hi> of the PARLIAMENTS Forces.</p>
            <p>Together with the Examination of the Meſſenger, in the Coller of whoſe Doublet the ſaid Letter was found.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>ORdered by the Commons in Parliament, That this Letter and Examination be forthwith printed and publiſhed:</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for EDW: HUSBANDS, February 27. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:155738:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:155738:2"/>
            <p>A Letter from Sergeant Major <hi>Ogle</hi> to Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſp,</hi> as appears by the Examination (herewith printed) of the Meſſenger, in whoſe coller the Letter was found, who was intercepted by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Goodwyn;</hi> Sergeant Major <hi>Ogle</hi> likewiſe being examined before a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, confeſſeth the Letter to be all of his own hand, and by him ſent to Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſp</hi> by the ſame Meſſenger, but affirms, that the Letter intends no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but to deſire a reſolution from Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſp,</hi> touching ſome lands which he had offered him formerly to ſell: And this is all he will yet confeſſe; and what appearance this has of truth, deducible from this Letter, let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judge.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:155738:3"/>
                  <head>A Letter of dangerous conſequence from Sergeant Major <hi>Ogle,</hi> to Sir <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Criſp</hi> at Oxford.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce your departure from hence, I writ you <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Letter which I hope came to your hands: If I had knowne of your boſome-friends com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you, I ſhould have ſent, and imparted that which now I cannot: But ſince you have the conveniency and ſafety of Mr. <hi>Collewells</hi> coming hither, Pray let me receive a finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, and hang no longer in ſuſpence, whether any thing is to be done or no in that buſineſſe we ſpoke. I want nothing but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to effect it, but in caſe there be either a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in the thing, or a diſhke or diſpute of me for the Actor, pray let me know; and in caſe therebe ſome reaſons which I am ignorant of, to hinder what we ſpoke of, then M. <hi>Colwell</hi> can tell you ſomewhat I wiſhed him to write to you, which upon the receit of money I ſhall bring along with me to you ſpeedily. In a word Three thouſand five hundred pound will ſerve
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155738:3"/>to effect that, which will be an extraordinary benefit and advantage, if not a finall happy concluſion to what we both deſire, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney if you will give Maſter <hi>Colwell</hi> order to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me with, Ile give him that Land and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery which I ſpoke to you in ſecurity for the ſame; And ſpeedily come to you well prepared when I ſhall take a full order for your ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: However pray let me know your poſitive determination, and of what account and recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (if any at all) I am there, which how bad or ſmall ſoever it be, I would willingly repair by this, or ſome other notable vvay vvherein I might be entruſted: your candidneſſe herein, I ſhall take for an extraordinary evidence of your friendſhip, vvhich till death I vvill requite by reſting</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your faithfull Friend to ſerve you, <hi>THEOPHILUS PHILOBRITANIS.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THe nevves here is, that the Commons ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday carried up their Votes to the Lords, vvith reaſons declaring their diſaſſent from concurring vvith the Lords in a Ceſſation of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155738:4"/>Armes and a Treaty: And that upon theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the Commons had Voted the disbanding both Armies preſently, and till that vvere done no Treaty upon the Propoſitions; which if his MAjESTY would aſſent unto, there ſhould be a Treaty and a Ceſſation of Armes tovvards a disbanding. One particular circumſtance I vvill acquaint you vvith in the carriage of this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vvhich vvas remarkeable. After the Lords had voted a Ceſſation of Armes and a Treaty, the next morning they ſent a Meſſage to the Commons for a conference to acquaint them with their Votes. While the Meſſengers tarry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their Anſwer (which uſually is very ſhort, either they will; or they will ſend an Anſwer by Meſſengers of their owne) it was ſo ordered that Colonell <hi>Manwaring,</hi> Captain <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey,</hi> Captain <hi>Titchburn,</hi> Captain <hi>Vnderwood,</hi> Captain <hi>Gore,</hi> and divers other Citizens, with Maſter <hi>Caſe,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Wodcocke</hi> and <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> with other Miniſters, came to the Houſe of Commons, and deſired to be heard, and to deliver ſome reaſons they had in the behalfe of the City, againſt a ceſſation of Armes and a Treaty: Whereupon there was preſent reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to call them in: But a Debate of almoſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155738:4"/>an hour, vvhether they ſhould be called in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the conference vvith Lords or no: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeverall Votes the Houſe was divided, and by ten Voices carryed to call them in firſt, and ſo they had the preheminence of the Lords. When they were called in, Colonell <hi>Manwaring</hi> was their ſpokes-man, and tendered a paper conteyning the reaſons: but they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to withdraw, and after ſome debate the paper was receiv'd, and they remind thanks. You may judge by this what likelyhood there is on other end ſave by the ſword. If it pleaſe God I come to you I ſhall more inlarge then I dare write. We hear his Majeſty had made Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> Baron of <hi>Glaſonbury,</hi> but he enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his honour a ſhort ſpace, for he and Six hundred men more of his are ſlain before <hi>Plunmouth.</hi> I have him that I ſent to you upon the Exchange yet, and the reſt you know of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do as I direct them. The God of Heaven direct us all aright, and ſettle the peace of this Church and Kingdom.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Pray let me hear ſpeedily from you.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155738:5"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Henry Commins,</hi> Servant to Maſter <hi>Daniel Colwell,</hi> one of the ſearchers of the Cuſtome-houſe London, taken before Colonell <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> and Colonell <hi>Bulſtrode,</hi> the <hi>16.</hi> of February, <hi>1642.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HE ſaith, that his Maſter went from his houſe in <hi>Bartholomew</hi> lane London, to Oxon, upon Friday laſt, with Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſps</hi> his Lady, and that Captain <hi>Ogle,</hi> dwelling over againſt Pallace-yard conduit Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, ſent by him a Letter to Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſp</hi> to Oxon: Which Letter the ſaid Captain did, together with his Maids help ſow up in the Coller of the Doublet of this Examinant, giving him a great charge to deliver the Letter carefully, and not to confeſſe from whom he had it: And there coming one to ſpeak with Captain <hi>Ogle,</hi> whiles he was ſowing in the Letter, he ſuddenly called this Examinant into his Cloſet, that he might not be diſcovered.</p>
            <p>And this incloſed Note, the Examinant ſaid, was ſent from Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſp</hi> his Servant, unto his Maſter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Comens.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
